there's a
a question from some friends somewhere
in the world
the question is in regards to sexual
desire is there anything beyond patient
is there anything beyond patient
endurance that one should consider doing
when certain thoughts arise certain
sexual thoughts arise
for example contemplating the different
body parts and organs
could that not serve as a tool for
trying to get rid of the unpleasant
feeling of pressure
and thus it would remain in the domain
of
eversion and craving it would be a
practice done out of
perversion and craving contemplating
those things so is it right to do
the contemplation the super
contemplation in times when there is no
unpleasant feeling or pressure to make
sure not to act out of the feeling oh yeah
not to act out of the feeling oh yeah
yeah no you should certainly that's
where you should do it
like when there is a pressure when you
are struggling to restrain yourself and
so on
yeah in endurance there you have to
endure it
and then asuba anything that can help
you endure it but when there is no
pressure and stuff yet that's where you
would actually be practicing asuba
because establishing those signs and
features of asuba
when the mind is clear and mindful oh
that will come in
on its own when the pressure of
centrality and sexuality arises
so so that's exactly the point to not
wait to practice asuba only
when there is a desire no that's
actually not going to be a proper subaru
that's just going to be an absolute
management of survival
when there is no desire that's that yeah
practice the subah dwell on it
and the clarity the disgust of the
nature of the body
will be established and even if you
don't then think about it all the time
next time sexuality presents itself
there will be the framework to the
extent that you've been cultivating it
when the mind was clear so the more you
do it
the the less the less of that pressure
will will be coming your way
because you can reflect that you are
liable to be sexual thoughts
exactly exactly you know you are so you
want to you want to you want to practice
that's always said like
you know even the sexual desire and the
pressure it's a symptom
of you being in a central domain
but you don't want to be only dealing
with that in symptoms of present you
want to recognize okay now symptoms are
gone i'm symptomless for the moment
i have all the space to move let me deal
with it
same for anger same for any unwholesome
state let me address it when it's not
there let me start contemplating what i
need to contemplate
and do what i need to do so when it does
come i'll have something to
you know to brace myself with
so that's exactly because if you when
you're doing a subaru when there is
essential desire
you're doing it because you want to get
rid of the central desire because it's
painful so it's never going to be as wholesome
so it's never going to be as wholesome
as as rightly ordered
as it would be if you're doing it when
you have no sense the central desire
present and then you choose to contemplate a
and then you choose to contemplate a
suba and dwell on it and maintain that
theme that clarity so you're neither a verse
that clarity so you're neither a verse
nor passionate
you're just looking at the clarity of
the body and that will settle in the
deepest and that's why when then as i said
and that's why when then as i said
sensuality comes aversion comes
well this framework will be there
because you have been cultivating it
it will be there on its own you wouldn't
need to where's my super now
oh if you invested the effort before the
sensuality came
a super the protection of that seeing
the ugly will be that
the more you develop it if it's not the
image you haven't developed sufficiently
so do it more
once you sustain the centrality and it
fades away start doing the work
because you can't do the work and endure
sensuality at the same time
sure enduring centrality is the form of
work but not as efficient work as it
would be when there is no centrality and
now you are
going down the way of abandoning
sensuality when the mind is clear of it
by contemplating ugly lack of
satisfaction that holds
all the suit as they talk about
positiveness the passiveness of food
the value of keeping the priest dwelling
on the unbroken virtue
when the sensuality comes you probably
just have to endure it until it goes
away and then you do the work then you don't
and then you do the work then you don't
think oh i'm safe because you went away
no no i survived so now i need to work
and there's that um
the noble disciples the lay person but
he was he was in arya
when he asked the buddha how cause like
you know for a noble disciple you know
dharma so clear understanding samadhi
all of that
but on some days sometimes sincerity
comes and the mind just doesn't see anything
and the mind just doesn't see anything
it doesn't matter
what you decide what's it that nothing
all the mind sees is the central desire
and the buddha said yeah for as long as
the uh even noble type of mind if he
hasn't withdrawn itself sufficiently
from sensuality hasn't understood the
peril of it the gratification that whole
thing hasn't experienced pleasure different to
hasn't experienced pleasure different to
the pleasure of sensuality i
pleasure renunciation the mind can still
remain attracted to it on
you know not as much as an unrestrained
producer in a boiling mind
but still it would go to it
so when it's not overwhelmed by enduring
the pressure sensuality
you do the work and you do a lot of it
because you have greater results of it
in other words it's more
it's it will be even more efficient to
do it when the mind is clear
so that's why yes you try and sustain
your mind as clear as possible
and do the work as much as possible
during that time sooner or later
aversion will come sensuality will come
sexual desire will come
that's when you endure it and then it
goes away back to work
and that also can prompt you to do more
work you realize oh it's still coming
so i'll endure it to do more work
then you did the work it's still coming
i'm not safe yet
doesn't matter i'll do the work it's
still coming i'll wait then i'll do the
work it's still coming i'll wait i'll do
the work it's still coming
oh it's coming less actually good i'll
do the work now you have confirmed that
your work works
oh it's coming slightly less but it's
come i'll do the work oh it's coming
even less now
i'll do even more work because now i
really know that this is working
and now it's not coming now i live in my
work which is i live in mindfulness
and in renunciation and that's around
you but when people do it in a sense of
but when people do it in a sense of
comes i do goes away i
succeeded no that's not the work and
that's why you never overcome it because
your measure is just when it goes away
no
no that your measure should be how
frequently keeps coming back
how powerful it is how much i have to
endure it and not abandon the work
work through that because you are
basically confirming directly for
yourself that it's working
you're not relying on a circumstance of
will sensuality come or not if it
doesn't come maybe i'm free
if it comes ah it doesn't matter you
already i'm doing the work
if it comes it will come it doesn't come
great when it comes i'll just see how
strong it is how much i have to endure
i'll endure it because i'm accomplished
in virtue
and then i'll do the same work more and
the time will come when it will stop
coming and there were many similarities
of the similar nature that it would have
gave like the flies
will keep trying to come and bite and
land if there is you know
raw whatever dirt present
but if it's if it's clean the flies will
buzz buzz buzz they'll find nothing
useful to land on their leave
or the crows coming and trying to pack
if there is fresh meat
rotten meat stinking or something like
when it's gone they'll leave they lose
interest and they will leave they will
be coming less and less frequently
until they stop coming because of the
work you're doing when they're not there
cleaning cleaning exactly polishing and
cleaning yeah
while they're not there that's why it's
important to
always keep that liability in your mind
as a criteria not like
well most of the time i don't have
central desire so i'm fine
great keep doing the work then then you
have no issues with doing the work
because the work is just the natural
mode of another hunt that you're
emulating through your work
natural mode of dispassion but it was
like oh i don't need to do the work because
oh i don't need to do the work because
it doesn't come as often it means
you never done any work that matters
because if you did you would realize can
it come
can it still come and that's exactly
that you know the levels of purity that
would still encourage monks to practice
is like
you know if you have mostly clean white
cloth one little stain
will be visible from afar because
everything else is clean
it will really stand out so yes it
doesn't come as often but can it still
come yes that is your work now
yes that is your work now
you still have to work
and that's how you clean it and free
yourself completely from it
so if it's coming frequently or not
frequently it doesn't matter you keep doing the
it doesn't matter you keep doing the
work when it's not there when it's there
you endure it and you keep reviewing
your mind
can it still come do i know that it
cannot come
am i sure then i will not be affected
not keep doing the work keep doing the
work what is making me liable to do what
is making me liable
keep doing the work of that restraint
accomplishment not acting out of one
wholesome all of that
reviewing things reviewing the nature of
things you are attracted to when there
is no attraction reviewing the nature of
things you are averse to when there is
no aversion
and cultivating and forcing your mind to
deal with it when there are no
unwholesome states present
overwhelming exactly because they will
be overwhelming you and then all you
would want to do is get rid of that so
then your whole practice revolves around
motivation i don't want this pain and that's not
i don't want this pain and that's not
the practice
so just so the work
when you're not overwhelmed by sexual
thoughts is
for example to review the body the
organs for example you know
in a very authentic clear manner not
just go anatomically without any
awareness but no no
things that you know you would be
attracted to that cause attraction
desire start seeing those things when there is
start seeing those things when there is
no desire learning how to see them
as unattractive not any random thing
that makes no difference to your
sensuality and then things basically you sensually
and then things basically you sensually
value or things you value when you're
averse when you're not a verse or not
not not with a mind of sensuality that's
not with a mind of sensuality that's
when you go back to those things
in that mindful sense and then learn to
see them in the opposite manner
attractive is unattractive hateful is
neutral not hateful why do i need to
hate this
and sustain those themes dwell on those
teams contemplate those themes
on the basis if you by the way all this
can be only done on the basis of your
own virtue
to not been contemplating virtue
practicing virtue keeping the virtue
all of this would just be abstract
theory and and response management
so then when it comes you will not be
too overwhelmed with i must deal with
this because otherwise i might break so
because otherwise i might break so
hopefully next time it become weaker and
weaker and weaker